<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>    
        <title>Vlad Kostyanetsky</title>
        <description>Hello! My name is Vlad, I'm business app developer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://kostyanetsky.me</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2024 15:11:48 +0700</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <title>Day Switcher for Obsidian</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/obsidian-day-switcher</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-obsidian-day-switcher</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2024 15:11:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>When you're actively working in daily notes in Obsidian, you often want to quickly peek into the note from yesterday or, conversely, for tomorrow. For example, when sorting today's tasks and wanting to postpone some of them for tomorrow.</p>
<p>I'm too lazy to type the exact date every time, so I wrote a <a href="https://gist.github.com/vkostyanetsky/6c70f00b817157f9b6e62ee89bade853" target="_blank">script</a> for this. It takes the note's date from its title (expects it to be in <abbr title="2024-08-17, for example.">ISO 8601</abbr> format) and generates a tooltip with links to yesterday's and tomorrow's notes. The day of the week is displayed in the header for additional convenience:</p>
<p><img alt="Example" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/obsidian-day-switcher/callout.jpg"/></p>
<p>The script is written for the <a href="https://github.com/blacksmithgu/obsidian-dataview" target="_blank">Dataview</a> plugin since I'm already using it for other tasks. In general, it can easily be adapted for <a href="https://github.com/SilentVoid13/Templater" target="_blank">Templater</a>, <a href="https://github.com/saml-dev/obsidian-custom-js" target="_blank">CustomJS</a>, or even turned into a standalone plugin (again, I'm too lazy to bother with that).</p>
<p>If you plan to use it:</p>
<ol>
<li>In the noteLink() function, specify the path to your daily notes folder (currently, the path contains a 'Days' folder for example; I mean the path is indicated in the Daily notes/Template file location setting);</li>
<li>Include the script in your daily note template (Daily notes/Template file location setting).</li>
</ol></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Clementine Will Remember That</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/clementine</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-clementine</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 23:09:32 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>When ChatGPT remembers a detail from a conversation for the future, it displays a "Memory updated" badge above its response. Like, got it:</p>
<p><img alt="Memory updated" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/clementine/memory-updated.jpg"/></p>
<p>Every time I see it, it makes me smile because it instantly reminds me of <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/207610/The_Walking_Dead/" target="_blank">The Walking Dead</a> and the meme “Clementine will remember that”. In that game, the characters surrounding the protagonist would remember his decisions, and it would influence their behavior. This included Clementine — a girl the main character saved at the beginning of the game.</p>
<p><img alt="Clementine will remember that" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/clementine/remember.jpeg"/></p>
<p>In the game, this mechanic was honestly implemented in a rather mediocre way, but when it comes to ChatGPT — it works. The attention to detail is so strong that sometimes I have to remind myself that I’m talking to a language model, not an extraordinarily attentive and very knowledgeable person.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Make Window a Door</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/make-my-window-a-door</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-make-my-window-a-door</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 19:26:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I was listening to <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/33MnSYLvtOrbj5zwfioEiH?si=19fec91123394826" target="_blank">Be Somebody</a> by Thousand Foot Krutch yesterday and suddenly caught the phrase “you made my window a door”. I used to think that this idiom is rather funny: like, damn, the idea to replace a window with a door somehow sounds unsafe. You can fall from the tenth floor, you know?</p>
<p>At the same time, the song is wonderful and not about that at all! I got curious and started digging around to find out what meaning native speakers put into it.</p>
<p>It turned out that it is actually about two different positions: a passive observer and an active participant. That is, if there is a window in front of you, you only look through it at something or someone. But you can open the door and finally do something. Hence, “when I could only see the floor you made my window a door” means something like “when my hands dropped, you helped me up”.</p>
<p>By the way, there is another similar idiom — “to be a better window than a door”. The abstraction here is the same: if a person is like a window, and not a door — they hardly ever let people close to them, making passive observers even out of people very close to them.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Yaga</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/yaga</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-yaga</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 01:21:21 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I accidentally remembered that six months ago, one of my colleagues threw a link to <a href="https://yaga.rt.ru" target="_blank">Yaga</a> into the work chat. It is a future (I guess) competitor of JIRA in Russia. Judging by the URL, the guys from Rostelecom are developing it. Here my curiosity was awakened — how is it there, did it take off?</p>
<p>Alas, but looks like nope. At least, the landing page has the “leave a request and wait for a response beep” vibe. Only a simplified version is available for smaller teams that I can't touch as well: being not in Russia and clicking on the “Start using” button leads me to a ban. Welp, next time, maybe.</p>
<p>The naming is clickbait, of course. But I’m not sure if it’s really a good choice. For example, “1C” may provoke forced jokes (One s! Odin's ass! Haha), but if you google this, you are more likely to find information about the platform or at least the vendor. Not a bunch of articles, fan fiction, fan art, or video games, as in the case of Yaga.</p>
<p>Moreover, some wrong associations come to mind. What does Baba Yaga reminds you of? A hut on chicken legs? It looks like an initially <a href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/evolution" target="_blank">poorly designed</a> application that was somehow remade right on production. A mortar? A crutch? Damn, if you look at it from the point of view of programmers — these are not red flags, but real scarlet banners fluttering in the wind :)</p>
<p>One more thing: I'm probably spoiled, but when I hear the word “Yaga”, the first thing that pops into my head is not a powerful witch from Slavic folklore, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaguar_(drink)" target="_blank">disgusting booze</a> from the 2000s.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Now Baba with Yaga are no longer redneck, but a patriotic programmer!</p>
<p>― colleague</p>
</blockquote></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Ibrahim</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/ibrahim</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-ibrahim</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 20:29:24 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Recently, I took a <a href="https://tough-dev.school/system-analysis" target="_blank">system analysis course</a>, which was taught by the guys from the “School of Strong Programmers”. I have two goals:</p>
<ol>
<li>First, I need to calibrate. I handle a dozen tech stacks that have different tool sets and concepts of beauty. This, of course, is a great development, but it distorts the perspective: I am drawn to solve the next problem, starting with minor technical things, simply because I am good at it. Meanwhile, if you look at the problem a little from above, think about it, and draw some diagrams, you will get a better or at least more meaningful solution. So I want to convince myself to do this more often.</li>
<li>Secondly, I need to learn how to write clear documentation for developers. In practice, I rarely get around to it, and when I do, I don’t have time to keep it up-to-date. In short, time is short, and I would at least like to do the paperwork somehow so that the reader grasps the idea more quickly.</li>
</ol>
<p>The course itself is made in the shape of iterations: every week you are told about the same project that the main character of the story, Ibrahim, is trying to design (that’s him on the landing page in the link above). Every week, there are more and more problems with this project, and the solutions that dude comes up with become more and more intricate.</p>
<p>In addition, students are regularly assigned homework for another project with similar issues. It needs to be analyzed and designed again and again, taking into account the new knowledge and limitations gained over the past week.</p>
<p>So far, it's going great. The main concern is a lack of time. I read relatively slowly and try to take notes on the most captivating or simply difficult passages. Meanwhile, there is a lot of material in the course, and all of it is interesting, even if you count only the main part of the content.</p>
<p>In addition, if you go to the additional links, you can even take away the saints. It takes six months, no less. I tried to read them at least diagonally, but it turned out to be a damn bad idea. I ended up seeing the main character of the course in a street advertisement :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Singapore Doll</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/singapore-doll</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-singapore-doll</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 23:46:57 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Is it possible to love your country's currency more than the people of Saudi Arabia? It is a rhetorical question: the answer is no.</p>
<p>I'm currently looking at the <a href="https://www.sama.gov.sa/en-US/FinExc/Pages/Currency.aspx" target="_blank">website</a> of their central bank. The country's currency is the Saudi riyal, and the Central Bank sets rates for other currencies in relation to it. Consequently, there is no point in asking the bank for the rate of the riyal itself. However, the website calmly suggests choosing it twice:</p>
<p><img alt="The selection form" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/singapore-doll/cb.png"/></p>
<p>For your information, the first option breaks the website, and the second one pedantically displays “1” for any date.</p>
<p>Another funny thing: colleagues seem to store currency names as 14-character strings. Otherwise, it is difficult to explain why, according to their data, Canada uses not the Canadian dollar but CANADIAN DOLLA, and Romania uses mysterious NEW ROMANIAN L instead of its leu. However, these two are rather lucky: Singapore, for example, conducts payments in SINGAPORE DOLL.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Non-Unique Metadata</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/data-history-duplication</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-data-history-duplication</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2024 18:28:35 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Once again, I came across a nasty bug when the platform broke the data history metadata table.</p>
<p>Outwardly, it looks like this: you update the database configuration, and when you try to restructure, the error “The data history metadata table contains duplicate records. Delete the duplicate records” pops up. The platform does not offer any clear way to find such records.</p>
<p><img alt="The data history metadata table contains duplicate records. Delete the duplicate records" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/data-history-duplication/error.png"/></p>
<p>The problem can be solved at the database level. The table referenced by the error is _DataHistoryMetadata. It contains metadata versions of each object for which data history is being maintained. This allows the platform to understand what attributes the object had at any point in time if the data history is maintained for the object.</p>
<p>How does it work? Well, when the list of an object’s attributes changes (for example, an attribute was added to the catalog), the platform writes its metadata: specifically, it adds a new entry to _DataHistoryMetadata and stores in it the current list of object attributes, as well as the version number of this list (for example, when history is enabled for an object, the first version of metadata is saved, when adding some attribute, the second version is saved, and so on).</p>
<p>The platform also puts a mark in the created record that this particular version of the object is the most actual, and then removes this mark from the version that was marked as actual before.</p>
<p>So, the problem is that the platform sometimes forgets to take the last step, and two versions appear in the table at once, marked as current. The Designer understands this but cannot do anything.</p>
<p>The solution follows from the algorithm above: you need to find conflicting versions and revoke the mark of actuality from the one that is older. It is better to use queries: data history is often enabled for a bunch of objects, and the list of their attributes is constantly changing — in general, there will be so many versions in the table that the devil will break his leg.</p>
<p>If you also encountered this problem and are therefore reading this text, you can use the <a href="https://gist.github.com/vkostyanetsky/6496c67e2b2fd3d064c4cafd16da0b79" target="_blank">queries</a> that I wrote:</p>
<ol>
<li>get-issues.sql checks that there is an issue: it looks for metadata versions that are also marked as actual.</li>
<li>fix-issues.sql removes the actuality mark from those versions that are actually outdated.</li>
</ol>
<p>Both queries are written for Microsoft SQL Server. If you use PostgreSQL, then <a href="https://gist.github.com/vkostyanetsky/75665ce04247e900743604eb386d1889" target="_blank">here they are</a> for this DBMS.</p>
<p>The queries will require a slight adaptation to a specific database: they use the _fld626 field, which is the data separator. In your _DataHistoryMetadata table, this field may be called differently, so you need to update its name to the current one. It will be difficult to make a mistake — the table has only one field with the _fld prefix.</p>
<p>P.S. Please bear in mind that the license agreement prohibits access to the database, bypassing the platform’s tools, so you can only go for such experiments if there are no other options left.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Main Issue of UUID</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/uuid-main-issue</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-uuid-main-issue</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 23:18:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I came across a <a href="https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en/unexpected-downsides-of-uuid-keys-in-postgresql/" target="_blank">good text</a> about the main problem that UUID brings with itself. It is also relevant for 1C: all platform reference objects (catalog items, documents, and so on) have their own UUID. They are stored in a database, actively used in searches, and, of course, extensively indexed (with all the ensuing consequences).</p>
<p>1C tries to suppress the issue by creating consistent UUIDs. It may not be perfect, but overall, this thing works, and the indexes turn out to be more or less compact. In general, the community has been talking about this for a long time: for example, the old <a href="https://forum.mista.ru/topic.php?id=801986" target="_blank">thread on Mista</a> (though the conversation here quickly turned into a chicken coop, and out of six dozen comments, at most one and a half are on point).</p>
<p>P.S. The remark about the probability of creating two identical UUIDs in one database made me laugh:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As an aside, for those worried about collisions: you should take up the lottery, since winning the jackpot twice in a row is a much more likely outcome than your system ever generating two identical random 128 bit numbers.</p>
</blockquote></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Screenshot With Sound</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/last-resort</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-last-resort</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:03:07 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Recently, we came up with the idea of dividing the internal ERP into several independent parts and organizing data exchange between them. We discussed the outlines of the task, the exchange model, transport, and roughly agreed on deadlines — in general, we did what we usually do.</p>
<p>I created a task for the stuff. We give them names in English, so I wrote in the first wording that came to mind.</p>
<p><img alt="Cut My Life Into Pieces" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/last-resort/last-resort.png"/></p>
<p>The title came out with sound. Okay, this one is funny, but what should I call it then? Well, let it be Distributed Internal ERP. Abbreviated... DIE?</p>
<p>I let the first one be. Long live Papa Roach :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Timesheet for Obsidian</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/obsidian-timesheet</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-obsidian-timesheet</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 17:50:58 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I made another <a href="https://obsidian.md" target="_blank">Obsidian</a> plugin, this time for <a href="https://help.obsidian.md/Plugins/Daily+notes" target="_blank">daily notes</a>. Draws a nice report: what tasks I worked on, what I did, and how much time I spent. I tried to describe how it works in the <a href="https://github.com/vkostyanetsky/ObsidianTimesheet" target="_blank">repository</a>; will be glad if it is useful to someone else!</p>
<p>Funny thing: for the examples in the README, I used issue numbers FBI-1, FBI-2, and so on. This isn't a reference to the X-Files or Twin Peaks — it's just the first thing that came to mind. The fact is that our internal project for the development of FirstBit ERP is called First Bit Internal, abbreviated as FBI. The main pool of tasks we work on lives in it.</p>
<p>We’re already used to it, but our colleagues outside the company always find our screenshots from JIRA or SonarQube amusing. Did you imagine that you were Agent Cooper? Well, I almost don’t even need to :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>