<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>    
        <title>Vlad Kostyanetsky</title>
        <description>Hello! My name is Vlad, I'm business app developer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://kostyanetsky.me</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 21:25:48 +0700</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <title>Diablo</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/diablo/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-diablo</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 21:25:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kVd6qeWoAxg" width="560"></iframe>
<p class="measure-wide">The nice release of the “We Are Doomed” IT podcast about developer burnout. No insights, but you can hear something useful. For example, what about not switching to pet projects after work, but close your laptop and go for a walk?</p>
<p class="measure-wide">I liked the analogy with video games, somewhere close to the middle:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="measure-wide">There was such a game — Diablo. RPG, all sorts of spells, you know. A character has mana and health, and when you have no mana to cast… Ha, I sound like a nerd! Well, nevermind. Briefly speaking, when you have no mana to cast, it's taken from your health.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="measure-wide">— Doctor Cat</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Hammer & Nails</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/hammer-and-nails/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-hammer-and-nails</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 21:47:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">I was developing payment documents in our configuration last week and came across an incredibly redundant solution to a primitive problem. Sorry, I can't keep to myself.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Just imagine: you have a document, which contains several tabular sections. Each of them has a comment field. You make a print form for this document; if at least one row of any TS contains a comment — you need to use one template 1, if there are no comments — template 2.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">The task is pretty primitive, isn't it? All of us have done something like this a million times. Just read the selection, use IsBlankString() on the comment field and load the appropriate template. Coffee time!</p>
<p class="measure-wide">However, instead of a short cycle, I saw this:</p>
<script src="https://gist.github.com/vkostyanetsky/e870d5bb3d2f23d93f3d17001eaef59b.js">Gist</script>
<p class="measure-wide">There is a chain of queries, in the lowest of which we scan all the TS (which, I remind you, we just raked out for printing). We are looking for comments in them, then we group the result several times and return it to the script.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Well, I'm not even talking about the load on the DBMS (I would venture to guess that this trick doesn't give a noticeable effect — after all, the selection is going to be small). It's just… Well… Checking a selection of rows is, like, five lines of code. Clear, simple, short, Sonar has no room to swear. How could you give birth to this? Because of great love for queries?</p>
<p class="measure-wide">You know what? I bet that it's the correct answer. I can almost see this programmer, who has just mastered the query language more or less tolerably. He is in the absolute delight of new opportunities, so… If all you have is a hammer, everything around looks like nails.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>No Comment</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/no-comment/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-no-comment</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 00:12:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">I did not notice when I gave up the habit of pedantically commenting on every method with which I have to work. This practice has some clever name for sure, but I don't care, to be honest. I mean the style when a description is added to every meaningful block of code, like this:</p>
<script src="https://gist.github.com/vkostyanetsky/afae4dee09d639f34156d6c02b29c2a5.js">Gist</script>
<p class="measure-wide">The meaning here is simple: when you dig in some dense legacy and run back and forth between chaotically scattered, big procedures — it is rather difficult to keep the logic of each of them in your head. The next cup of coffee will wash everything away. Therefore, such notes greatly speed up orientation on the ground, and the more time passes between approaches to the code, the more noticeable the effect.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">However, at some point it became clear that this know-how is just a crutch supporting the frankly crappy code design. If you have a long procedure or function - take a breath, sit down and cut the fatty one into smaller methods. You will save both time and nerves, and you will figure out the code faster, and you will delight SonarCube.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Nerd View</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/nerdview/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-nerdview</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 18:35:56 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide"><img alt="A chat with my daughter" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/nerdview/telegram.png"/></p>
<p class="measure-wide">On the screenshot above my little one is just letting me know where she is: walking down the street, at the school, at a playground. It's not her fault that I have a sort of nerd view: when I look at this chat I see nothing but code on Gherkin, which is just a bit broken. A little patch here and there and it will be fine :-)</p>
<pre><code>And I exit home
Then I enter school
And I exit school
Then I gonna swing
</code></pre>
<p class="measure-wide">We use Gherkin to write our autotests for <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://github.com/Pr-Mex/vanessa-automation" target="_blank">Vanessa Automation</a>. I can't say I've made very many of them, especially in comparison with some of my colleagues… Well, it seems like I've made them enough to twist the reality a few.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Ninth Wave</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/ninth-wave/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-ninth-wave</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 05:21:32 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">Yesterday morning, I was buying gifts for my women. While a florist was makings bouquets for me, we had a small talk and I suddenly caught her eye. She was looking at the growing crowd of customers with calmness and a clearly readable shadow of doom. This is probably how sailors looking at a surging wave which is about to bury their boat :-)</p>
<p class="measure-wide">People outside the flower industry grin sometimes — they say, eight of March is such a magical holiday for all the florists who make a fortune in ten hours. Well, income is really good these days, but literally anybody who has ever worked in this sphere more often associates the holiday (and a couple of days before it, by the way) with a monstrous strain on health and nerves.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">I can say that I got off cheaply: was just deploying and servicing some IT of a local net of flower shops, nothing more (by the way, I want to proudly <a class="link blue dim bb" href="http://rosetta.florist/" target="_blank">recommend</a> my former colleagues!). Nonetheless, the smell of flowers caused me Vietnam syndrome for a long time :-)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Snowboard Effect</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/snowboard-effect/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-snowboard-effect</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 13:58:43 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide"><a href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/snowboard-effect/standing.jpg" target="_blank"><img alt="Standing!" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/snowboard-effect/standing-thumbnail.jpg"/></a> <a href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/snowboard-effect/sitting.jpg" target="_blank"><img alt="Sitting!" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/snowboard-effect/sitting-thumbnail.jpg"/></a></p>
<p class="measure-wide">You're sliding down the side of a mountain and trying to feel an equilibrium point, for the hundredth time. However, your nagging back is the only thing you're able to feel, and the Vaas speech from Far Cry 3 isn't going out of your mind.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="measure-wide">Did I ever tell you what the definition of insanity is? Insanity is doing the exact… Same fucking thing… Over and over again expecting… Shit to change… That. Is. Crazy.</p>
<p class="measure-wide"><em>― Vaas Montenegro, Far Cry 3</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p class="measure-wide">Surprisingly, you're certainly satisfied with the trip when it's done.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">There's some kind of magic in it.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>A Principle of Non-Judgemental Attitude</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/non-judgmental-attitude/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-non-judgmental-attitude</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Sep 2018 16:36:53 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">There is a good <a class="link blue dim bb" href="http://maximilyahov.ru/blog/all/mne-ok/" target="_blank">note</a> from Maxim Ilyahov about a way of analyzing something which doesn't concern you but annoys you anyway. It's reminded me of an American principle of non-judgemental attitude which I've <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://www.facebook.com/lilya.kim/posts/490845771117074" target="_blank">learnt</a> in Facebook a couple of years ago. As for me, it uses different words to make the same point.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">By the way, this principle presents in Russia too — there is even a famous adage “don't be judgemental so you won't be judged”. What a pity for us that it isn't so widespread yet.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Beware the Daughter of the Sea</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/jaina/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-jaina</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2018 16:19:10 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">Natalia O'Shea has sung a Jaina's song in a Russian version of a trailer for a future update of World of Warcraft. As for me, she's extraordinary good in it — I mean, she knows how to make a proper mood and season a speech with steel.</p>
<iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5j-S448XC8k" width="560"></iframe>
<p class="measure-wide">By the way, speaking about her and “Melnitsa” as a whole thing — all of their most powerful songs are about something particular. We were at a concert dedicated to the “Luciferase” release and it's hard to compare, seriously. Perhaps, I didn't know something essential to understanding a context, but sometimes it was even barely possible to figure out a story which I was hearing.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Just watch a video I posted under. You don't need to know something special about the World of Warcraft universe, do you? For example, I haven't played WoW and not planning to do it, but the end of the song literally creeps me out :-)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>HPMoR Printing</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/hpmor-printing/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-hpmor-printing</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 19:00:55 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">Perhaps you already know that Eliezer Yudkowsky's “Methods of Rationality” in Russian is going to be published as a standard book (thanks to “Evolution” and other information partners), but I still want to remind again.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">The book is really good, I had <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/hpmor" target="_blank">written</a> about it a couple of years ago. It teaches useful things in such an attractive way that it's really hard to stop reading. The whole text is in public access, but if you want a hard copy — you can <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://planeta.ru/campaigns/hpmor" target="_blank">make a request</a> now.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>FCE Results</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/fce-results/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-fce-results</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 10:48:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">Cambridge just sent me results of my FCE exam in June and — dramatic drum roll — I passed it! According to the statement of results, I made a bunch of mistakes in writing tasks but particularly took it out during a Speaking test. It's a pity that examiners don't give comments and reasons so it's hard to estimate the results properly; however, it's quite clear what to do next :) My English teacher said that Cambridge used to provide an overall score only earlier and it sounded like “take it any way you want, dear pretenders”.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Well, I guess I should begin my preparation for CAE in the next year.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Speaking about languages, I remembered Feynman with his famous “Surely You're Joking”. Among many things, he told that he learned to play on a frigideira when he lived in Brazil and had reached so high level of skill that he served as a model for local musicians.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="measure-wide">My theory is that it's like a person who speaks French who comes to America. At first they're making all kinds of mistakes, and you can hardly understand them. Then they keep on practicing until they speak rather well, and you find there's a delightful twist to their way of speaking their accent is rather nice, and you love to listen to it.</p>
<p class="measure-wide"><em>― Richard Feynman, ”Surely You're Joking, Mr. Feynman!”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p class="measure-wide">As for me, there is a lot of efforts between “all kinds of mistakes” and “love to listen”, but it is such a good synopsis. Working on it!</p></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>