<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>    
        <title>Vlad Kostyanetsky</title>
        <description>Hello! My name is Vlad, I'm business app developer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://kostyanetsky.me</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 23:33:52 +0700</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <title>Easter Eggs</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/easter-eggs</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-easter-eggs</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 23:33:52 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><img alt="Thank you, Mario!" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/easter-eggs/mario.jpg"/> <img alt="Awaiting Signal" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/easter-eggs/mothership.jpg"/></p>
<p>A couple of Easter eggs hidden inside FirstBit ERP. They're tucked away for the developers: in the first case, users see just the form title and notification text, while in the second, they see the standard "waiting for connection" message.</p>
<p>I like to add little things like this from time to time — it helps to keep things fun, even when the task isn’t the most exciting or I’m just feeling tired. If you haven’t checked out Bystronovsky’s "<a href="https://collab.ldwg.ru/stressless-design" target="_blank">Design Without Stress</a>", you really should — no way I could explain it better myself.</p>
<p>By the way, here’s another Easter egg! Not from our ERP this time, but from a new tool we’re making for automated database updates. We're building it just for ourselves, so we can joke around with the user a bit :)</p>
<p><img alt="Nice try, Marty!" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/easter-eggs/marty.jpg"/></p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>ERP Development In English</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/across-meeting</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-across-meeting</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 23:54:12 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mZwHTbu285A" width="560"></iframe>
<p>Our lead developer recently shared some insights about our work — specifically, developing ERP systems on 1C for the UAE and, more recently, Saudi Arabia. The session was hosted by the online English school Across, so the audience was spot-on: Russian-speaking folks interested in building careers and exploring international markets.</p>
<p>Overall, it turned out pretty cool, especially as a language practice. Just a reminder: learning foreign languages is still one of the best ways to give your brain a workout, and it’s also super accessible. There’s no shortage of resources, communities, and interest-based clubs out there — you just need the motivation :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Mysterious Code</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/safe-code</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-safe-code</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 23:25:22 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><img alt="Code" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/safe-code/code.jpg"/></p>
<p>Somewhere on the streets of Tbilisi. As a big fan of the Dishonored series, I just couldn’t walk past this. I’m sure there’s a safe nearby that this code unlocks!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Go Away, Negativity!</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/negativity</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-negativity</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 23:09:32 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><img alt="Chichilaki" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/negativity/chichilaki.jpg"/></p>
<p>The white things in the background are called chichilaki. It’s a kind of Georgian New Year tree (in practice, it’s finely shaved hazelnut branches). It’s believed to absorb all the accumulated negativity, so after the holidays, it’s supposed to be burned (along with the negativity).</p>
<p>Turns out, that last part is a bit of a challenge. The local police (and especially the fire department) view this good old tradition with suspicion — and understandably so (a chichilaki can be as tall as a person, making it quite the torch). So, we were advised to simply toss the "negativity-charged" chichilaki into the trash to avoid getting fresh troubles. Or donate it to the zoo — apparently, the animals play with them and even use them to clean their teeth.</p>
<p>That last part made me smile. Getting rid of negativity with the help of cats — what a surprise. Big, toothy cats, sure, but still cats!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>A Little Bit Of Surgery</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/bit-of-surgery</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-bit-of-surgery</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 22:40:24 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>A few years ago, I stumbled upon a story about a programmer who had to debug software controlling a surgical robot — right in the middle of an operation. That blew my mind, to be frank.</p>
<p>Today, my colleague and I were fixing a 1C cluster with databases running on 1cFresh. After migrating it to a neighboring server, the thing suddenly started acting up. Long story short: trying to print a document would send the client app into its death throes.  </p>
<p>While we were knee-deep in troubleshooting, I had this thought: sure, it doesn’t look as terrifying as debugging software that someone’s life literally depends on. But if you think about all the clients sitting on edge because their business is grinding to a halt... Well, who knows where the stress levels are higher?  </p>
<p><strong>P.S. Nerdy details for the curious.</strong> During the migration, the permissions for the server cache folder didn’t transfer properly. This led to a funny (well, not so funny) effect: the logs would happily land there, but session data wouldn’t.  </p>
<p>So, when someone opened a print form, the configuration tried saving it to the storage, and rphost, in turn, attempted to shove it into the session cache. Here’s where things went sideways: the worker' process (probably) got slapped on the wrist by the OS. Due to (apparently) some funky file system event handling in the platform, the exception wasn’t caught, so the poor thing had no better idea than to kill the session. Naturally, this caused the client process to crash.  </p>
<p>We fixed the permissions, rebooted the cluster, and voilà! The problem was gone.  </p>
<p><img alt="End of Report" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/bit-of-surgery/report.jpeg"/></p>
<p>All other hypotheses — cluster manager acting up, lack of hardware resources, configuration bugs, client-side issues, broken security profiles, network problems between the client and server — got tossed out during the diagnostics process.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Vaguely Familiar Logo</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/vaporia</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-vaporia</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 17:37:06 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><del>Meanwhile, OpenAI opened a branch in Tbilisi</del> Actually, they just sell vapes here, and the logo designer was probably inspired by clouds of steam. But every time I walk by, it still catches my eye :)</p>
<p><img alt="Vaporia" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/vaporia/vaporia.jpg"/></p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Creepy Graveyard</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/creepy-graveyard</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-creepy-graveyard</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 23:23:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Still learning 3D in my free time. Here's my first somewhat independent project after finishing a <a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/blender-environments-megacourse-create-3d-environments/" target="_blank">course</a> recently.</p>
<p><a href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/creepy-graveyard/creepy-graveyard.png" target="_blank"><img alt="Creepy Graveyard" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/creepy-graveyard/creepy-graveyard.png"/></a></p>
<iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mraGFR_Tr5k" width="560"></iframe>
<p>Of course, there are plenty of issues: the models, the colors, the composition... Honestly, pretty much everything. Good thing the scene is set at night with fog, so it's easy to hide the worst spots. I wouldn't be surprised if the course creators picked this setting on purpose to keep beginners from getting too discouraged :)</p>
<p>That said, I'm happy with the result. At this stage, perfectionism feels more like an enemy than a friend. And hey, it’s definitely better than my last attempt! Back then, I was totally green in Blender and scared to deviate even slightly from the instructor: ten minutes of watching, ten minutes of copying.</p>
<p>That approach works at the very beginning, but it doesn't help you learn how to solve problems. This time, I watched a few lessons back-to-back for about an hour or two, then tried to figure things out on my own. I only went back to the videos when I was completely stuck. Feels like I’m actually retaining a lot more this way.</p>
<p>Long story short, the thing is done. On to the next one!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Summary to Slack</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/slack-summary</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-slack-summary</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 13:22:54 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I found a <a href="https://gist.github.com/vkostyanetsky/b0807f2df2501bbeeb97c95a977f3e23" target="_blank">script</a> that I wrote a couple of years ago for our work GitLab. In short, we run our development repository through a barrage of tests on Vanessa daily, resulting in a nice report showing how many tests passed, which ones failed, the reasons for failures, and so on.</p>
<p>The report needs to be analyzed regularly, at least at a glance. Of course, we haven’t seen fully "green" tests in a long time, and that’s expected: for example, in the case of interdependent development, commits can break the checked functionality, and the tests still need adjustments. However, keeping a pulse on it is still essential.</p>
<p>To simplify this routine, I expanded the pipeline code a bit: after generating the report, GitLab first creates a brief summary (client type, database type, test statistics) and sends it to Slack.</p>
<p><img alt="Report" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/slack-summary/report.jpg"/></p>
<p>As a bonus, it’s now easier to answer the philosophical question, "who broke everything". Most often, it’s the author of the first commit on which the Scenarios Failed metric in the screenshot above hit the ceiling :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Log &amp; Bug</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/butterfly</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-butterfly</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 20:45:16 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I love digging into the origins of words from time to time. For example, "log" comes from maritime terminology and literally means a log: a wooden float attached to a rope, which was thrown overboard from a ship. The rope had knots tied at regular intervals, and by counting how many knots unwound in a certain amount of time, sailors could determine the speed of the ship.</p>
<p>These measurements were recorded in the ship's journal, which was also called a log. Over time, the term started being used for any kind of record or journal of events, and in IT, the word got a second life :)</p>
<p>Or take "bug" — well, you’ve probably heard about this one. A moth, which messed with a computer’s operation over seventy years ago, was documented in the log as "the first actual case of a bug being found". The insect gained a kind of digital immortality: now any mistake, especially in a program, is called a bug.</p>
<p>(It’s just a pity that it wasn’t a prettier insect — like a butterfly, for instance? That would’ve added a touch of romance to our work)</p>
<p>(Though, if you think about it... maybe "bug" isn’t such a bad option after all. "Butterfly" is a bit too long. Besides, someone would’ve shortened it to "butt," and right now, we’d be fixing butts instead of bugs)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>ChatGPT Mimicry</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-love</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 14:57:41 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Colleagues are actively <a href="https://t.me/denissexy/8767" target="_blank">experimenting</a> with o1-preview from OpenAI: the model turned out to be genuinely interesting. Unfortunately, tasks for it don’t come up too often — regular 4o handles most day-to-day stuff just fine. Bug-finding in code, analyzing medical tests in an unfamiliar language, or trying to recall the name of a childhood book with only a vague recollection of the plot — I can’t easily think of anything it wouldn’t handle.</p>
<p>It’s always fascinating to see how the AI reasons, jokes, and generally tries to act human. I’d say it won’t pass the Turing test just yet, but every now and then, it comes eerily close.</p>
<p><img alt="Carrot" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love/carrot.jpg"/> <img alt="Fists" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love/fists.jpg"/> <img alt="Jokes" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love/joke.jpg"/></p>
<p>The answer below made me smile. Even leaving philosophy aside — looks like Skynet is off the table! :) Though, I’m afraid the future from the <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/282140/SOMA/" target="_blank">SOMA</a> ending is still possible.</p>
<p><img alt="Love" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love/love.jpg"/></p></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>