<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>    
        <title>Vlad Kostyanetsky</title>
        <description>Hello! My name is Vlad, I'm business app developer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://kostyanetsky.me</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2022 20:09:31 +0700</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <title>Do Not Confuse</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/do-not-confuse/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-do-not-confuse</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2022 20:09:31 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide"><img alt="Code" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/do-not-confuse/do-not-confuse.png"/></p>
<p class="measure-wide">If the type of operation is the sale of goods or real estate, then open the common form AdvancesPickFormWithVAT with the parameters defined in the PickParameters structure. The callback is EditPrepaymentOffsetEnd method, defined in the same module; pass it the AdditionalParameters structure. The form needs to be opened so that it locks the whole interface.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">However, if the type of operation is a return to the supplier, then open the general form AdvancesPickFormWithVAT with the parameters defined in the PickParameters structure. The callback is the EditPrepaymentOffsetEnd method, defined in the same module; pass it the AdditionalParameters structure. The form needs to be opened so that it locks the whole interface.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">I hope you won't confuse.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>No More Google Fonts</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/no-more-google-fonts/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-no-more-google-fonts</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 20:25:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide"><a href="https://twitter.com/PixelAmbacht/status/1494272370076536840" target="_blank"><img alt="Tweet" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/no-more-google-fonts/snap-tweet-PixelAmbacht-1494272370076536840.png"/></a></p>
<p class="measure-wide">A year ago, damn it. Okay, hello everyone! Johnny Slowpoke is here! Today we will throw out Google Fonts from my blog. I used to load the main font (PT Sans) from this service, but it makes almost no sense without cross-domain caching. Frankly speaking, the only point to do this further is if a server on which the site is running is slow, so it is faster to load fonts from Google. </p>
<p class="measure-wide">I host my blog on GitHub servers and have no complaints about performance. So, I'm self-hosting PT Sans now, and you know what? The difference is dramatic. When updating a page before, there was clearly a noticeable delay between loading the page and loading the font. For now, it is barely recognizable. If you have a blog and want to try to self-host fonts — here is a cool <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://google-webfonts-helper.herokuapp.com/fonts" target="_blank">service</a> that solves the problem in a few clicks.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Don't forget to put a big, nice star on the <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://github.com/majodev/google-webfonts-helper" target="_blank">repository</a>!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Totals of 2021</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/totals-of-2021/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-totals-of-2021</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 13:25:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">It is a bit late to sum up, isn't it? Well, the previous couple of months have been, um, tight, so I had no actual time  to sit down and think. Now I'm on vacation for 2021 – so no time like the present. I'm writing, like, from the past.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Write out each achievement doesn't attract me at all. The year definitely turned out to be good: I did a lot of complex work on FirstBit ERP (wrote new modules, rewrote existing ones, crushed bugs, wrote functional and load tests – yes, there were countless things). This had a good effect both on the configuration itself and on the profits of my company. In addition, I passed 1C expert exam and a PostgreSQL professional exam. Hip-hip-hooray.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">There were fails as well. I still feel lazy to jot them down, but the main one is obvious – I became monstrously fat and instead of losing ten kilograms (that was the original plan) – I gained five more.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Looking back, the root of most of the problems over the past year is this: I focused too much on task flow. They were all interesting in their own way, from a carefully written technical task to challenges like “find a problem in the code using your witcher's instincts”. You do one task, another, a third, a hundredth, and you do not notice that you have ignored almost everything except work. As a result, you get a lot of experience, but the world dries up to the Configurator window and there is no strength to somehow apply this experience. Unhealthy bullshit.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">In short, if you imagine me as a character in some video game, it looks like this: attack and intelligence have grown noticeably over the year, but health, agility, charisma, and almost everything else in general, have dropped. Now I need to do something to deal with this mess.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">You know what? I'll take ten kilometers run for a start.</p>
<p class="measure-wide"><a href="https://twitter.com/EffinBirds/status/1329575199667347459" target="_blank"><img alt="Tweet" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/totals-of-2021/snap-tweet-EffinBirds-1329575199667347459.png"/></a></p>
<p class="measure-wide">Maybe, birdie, maybe.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Reuse Carefully</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/reuse-carefully/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-reuse-carefully</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 09:00:11 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">I'll tell you about a funny and a little embarrassing case that I took apart in January. The essence in a nutshell: a huge auto-test based on Vanessa, which is intended to check the VAT calculation, falls somewhere near the end.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">I start investigating. First, I look at the screenshots in Allure: OK, the reason is obvious – in one of the documents, the conditional appearance for the field with the VAT amount doesn't work. The test expected it to be unavailable if the VAT rate is zero, but it turned out to be available somehow.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">It's a mess, it needs to be fixed! I look at the condition in the code: well, it locks the field if the VAT rate is in the list of “zero” rates (list of VAT rates whose rate is equal to zero). Everything appears to be simple and logical. What the hell could possibly go wrong here?</p>
<p class="measure-wide"><a href="https://twitter.com/EffinBirds/status/1489980393675702281" target="_blank"><img alt="Tweet" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/reuse-carefully/snap-tweet-EffinBirds-1489980393675702281.png"/></a></p>
<p class="measure-wide">Well, I try to reproduce the bug manually. And there, all of a sudden, everything is nice: the conditional appearance works as it should. Floating bug, or what? I run the auto-test again, at the right moment I jump in with the debugger and find some outright garbage: in the list of “zero” rates, besides themselves, there are a bunch of empty links!</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Frankly speaking, I was scratching the back of my head. The document receives this list from the common module with <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://gist.github.com/vkostyanetsky/5ec036ee148606aad9caefbc9305bfb0" target="_blank">this code</a>. An empty ref from here, even theoretically, cannot be obtained. Moreover, the module has the “Reuse Return Values” option ​​enabled, and the function is actually executes once somewhere at the beginning of the test, before all complex data manipulations. So, the test cannot affect it in any way, in theory.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Is it a dead end? Well, experienced colleagues have probably already guessed everything, but I had to dance around the bug  and even check the <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://its.1c.ru/db/v8std/content/724/hdoc" target="_blank">standard</a>, until got the following: <strong>return values ​​cache in 1C can be changed</strong>. I mean, not by calling RefreshReusableValues​​(), but by changing reusable values directly.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">How? Well, if you get some values ​​from a cached common module, and they are not of a primitive type (string, number, etc.), you will not get the value itself, but a pointer to it somewhere in memory. You write this pointer to a variable and try to change it – you change the cache.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">It's that simple, yes. This is what happened in my case: the form of another document called the method that generates the list of “zero” rates. Having received a list of values, it added an empty ref to it and used it in its logic. Thus, each time this form opens, the list cache contains more and more empty refs, which eventually broke the document at the other end of the configuration.</p>
<p class="measure-wide"><a href="https://twitter.com/EffinBirds/status/1488165946342662144" target="_blank"><img alt="Tweet" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/reuse-carefully/snap-tweet-EffinBirds-1488165946342662144.png"/></a></p>
<p class="measure-wide">In a good way, the platform should throw exceptions when developer trying to change the cache, but until this happens, you have to take care yourself. For example, when developing cached modules, return immutable data types from them (FixedStructure instead of Structure, FixedArray instead of Array, and so on). True, this is not a 100% protection: firstly, fixed types are not applicable everywhere, and secondly, even in the latest versions of the SSL, this is far from being done everywhere. Do you know many configurations not based on SSL?</p>
<p class="measure-wide">Sonar also know nothing about the problem, as well as less popular software. No silver bullet, in short – check your code, look at the code of your colleagues and try not to forget about another elegant way to bang ourselves in the foot.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Infostart Event 2021</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/infostart-event-2021/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-infostart-event-2021</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 23:40:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">Last week I visited Moscow for <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://event.infostart.ru/2021_msk/" target="_blank">Infostart Event 2021</a>:</p>
<ul class="measure-wide">
<li>Listen to numbers of interesting reports — check;</li>
<li>Meet a few cool people in real life — check;</li>
<li>Chat with friends — check!</li>
</ul>
<p class="measure-wide">As a result, I suddenly felt rested despite the flights, stress, and fuss. I think it's because I'm working remotely, so it was really cool to look at so many colleagues in real life (not as a stream of electrons, I mean).</p>
<p class="measure-wide">In order not to <s>get up</s> to fly twice, I passed the <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://postgrespro.ru/education/exam/DBA1-10" target="_blank">first test</a> for PostgreSQL administration in the PostgresPro office. There are three more tests ahead, and the final one does not exist at all yet — but the walking one will master the road, I guess.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Matryoshka</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/matryoshka/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-matryoshka</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 17:14:56 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">A few days ago, there was a link to 1Ci certificate in the team chat (a colleague passed their junior <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://academy.1ci.com/courses/1c-junior-developer" target="_blank">course</a>). I go over and see no auth form, no errors — I just get a PDF file. Everything is OK, right? Well, then I open the file:</p>
<p class="measure-wide"><img alt="Error.pdf" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/matryoshka/not-your-certificate.png"/></p>
<p class="measure-wide">Honestly, I am even delighted. We need to implement this UX in our products: you press, for example, the “print” button for a document, and it gives you a PDF! And inside it — a link to another PDF! And inside it — “entity is not filled”, so go fill.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">You can sell it as a Russian way of dealing with errors. This is, like, for historical reasons! Blame all the damned matryoshkas, and <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koschei" target="_blank">Koschei</a> with his needle. It is, as you remember, in the egg, and it is in the duck, which is in the rabbit, tucked into the chest, and further along the chain of nesting.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Second Monitor Management via Console</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/2nd-monitor-and-console/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-2nd-monitor-and-console</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 16 Oct 2021 19:55:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">I have two monitors. I use the second one during meetings in Zoom or when playing together with friends (in both cases it's convenient to bring the people's cameras there). There are more examples when it's useful, but often the device is simply idle. In order not to be distracted, I decided to turn it off.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">What is the ambush here: it is inconvenient to enable or disable the second monitor via OS (a few clicks, and you need to scroll, and all the time you get confused where to go — in “Screen settings” or “Personalization”). I would like one command, and the command on a hotkey. And, ideally, from the script to rule all this.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">I did not find the script, but I found a ready-made utility — MultiMonitorTool. It's free. Works under the Windows 10 without problems. The commands below turn on / off the 2nd monitor:</p>
<pre><code>MultiMonitorTool.exe / disable 2
MultiMonitorTool.exe / enable 2
MultiMonitorTool.exe / switch 2
</code></pre>
<p class="measure-wide">For some reason, when you turn on a monitor via enable or switch, it's positioned incorrectly sometimes (for example, before it was turned off, it was on the right, and after turning it on, it was on the left). This is fixable. First, let's save the configuration at the moment when both monitors are on:</p>
<pre><code>MultiMonitorTool.exe / SaveConfig Monitors.cfg
</code></pre>
<p class="measure-wide">And then, when you need to turn on the monitor, load the saved config:</p>
<pre><code>MultiMonitorTool.exe / LoadConfig Monitors.cfg
</code></pre>
<p class="measure-wide">The utility can do a lot more (for example, one of the commands flips application windows between monitors). Follow the link above for the description.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Top Salaries</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/top-salaries/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-top-salaries</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2021 16:49:35 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><blockquote>
<p class="measure-wide">There is a path to a CSV file. You need to open it, read the header (first line), find the Salary column and display the top 10 salaries.</p>
<p class="measure-wide"><em><a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://t.me/nikitonsky_chat/26402" target="_blank">Link</a></em></p>
</blockquote>
<p class="measure-wide">Threw in my <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://gist.github.com/tonsky/881d5d8c4fbed818fe2905a7591a91e0#file-vkostyanetsky-1c" target="_blank">two cents</a> just to complete the picture. If you forget about stability, readability, and performance — you can cut it in half. Here it was obvious from the very beginning that it would be shorter in bash and clearer in Python, so I just wrote it as I was used to.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">What was useful: there are a bunch of examples in other languages ​​in the comments to the post. Frankly speaking, I haven’t come across some of them; it was really curious to look at the syntax and try to understand the way to solve the task.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">In general, the whole story reminded Eugene Stepanishev's <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://bolknote.ru/tags/beer99/" target="_blank">hobby</a> — to write the output of the American “beer song” in all languages ​​in a row. By the way, Tonsky's issue looks as fun for me too — too trivial to seriously compare something on its basis.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">What was funny: for a couple of <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://t.me/nikitonsky_pub/201?comment=26703" target="_blank">colleagues</a>, the 1C code caused such acute vision problems that they considered it necessary to report it :-) I partly understand the desire to assert itself on the stereotype “1C is bad, mkay?”, but it's the wrong case. The preference in syntax is nothing but a matter of taste, and besides it, the solution in 1C is no different from solutions in any other language without a built-in library for parsing CSV.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Building This Site on GitHub</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/build-on-github/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-build-on-github</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 22:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p class="measure-wide">For the last year this site has been working on a simple platform: statics, GitHub and my domain. All the pages were pre-generated and placed in a GitHub's <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://github.com/vkostyanetsky/kostyanetsky.me-static" target="_blank">repository</a> with <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank">GitHub Pages</a> enabled.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">I collected statics using a script. It was working with a list of text files, pedantically arranged in folders. The script rummaged through them and generated HTML files. Then I manually pushed them to the repository.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">This scheme worked well, but the number of clicks annoyed me. Here is the script pull, and there is the script pull, and then you have to tinker with the git. I wanted it to be simpler.</p>
<p class="measure-wide">At some point, I figured out that not only the deployment of statics, but also the assembly can be shifted onto the shoulders of GitHub. I put together some thoughts and added two more repositories:</p>
<ol class="measure-wide">
<li>A <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://github.com/vkostyanetsky/kostyanetsky.me" target="_blank">repository</a> of initial data. Here I put the content of the site: the text files and a bit of metadata (page titles, dates of pages creation, tags for notes, and so on).</li>
<li>A <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://github.com/vkostyanetsky/BlogBuilder" target="_blank">repository</a> of the script for generating statics. In addition to the script itself, I put various assets here (icons, styles, manifests — in general, everything that doesn't need to be generated every time, but you have to “put” it next to the resulting HTML).</li>
</ol>
<p class="measure-wide">Then I wrote an <a class="link blue dim bb" href="https://github.com/vkostyanetsky/kostyanetsky.me/blob/main/.github/workflows/main.yml" target="_blank">action</a> that wakes up with every push to the repository with the initial data. Shortly, its logic:</p>
<ol class="measure-wide">
<li>Clone the repository with statics and the repository with the generating script;</li>
<li>Update the repository with statics using the generating script;</li>
<li>Push changes of the repository with static to the main branch;</li>
<li>Notify the owner (me) via Telegram.</li>
</ol>
<p class="measure-wide">Voilà! Now, whenever the repository with the original data changes, the GitHub immediately (well, as soon as possible — within a minute) updates the repository with the site and deploys it via GitHub Pages. A bonus is a web interface to manage the site (in fact, the GitHub site). No Code. :-)</p>
<p class="measure-wide">While I'm at it, I added links for editing pages directly to the site (the pencil icon in the upper-right corner). This is intended as a convenience for me, but anyone who finds a typo can send a PR. Thank you in advance!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Diablo</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/diablo/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-diablo</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 21:25:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kVd6qeWoAxg" width="560"></iframe>
<p class="measure-wide">The nice episode of the “We Are Doomed” IT podcast about developer burnout. No insights, but you can hear something useful for yourself. I liked the analogy with video games, somewhere close to the middle:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="measure-wide">There was such a game — Diablo. RPG, all sorts of spells, you know. A character has mana and health, and when you have no mana to cast… Ha, I sound like a nerd! Well, nevermind. Briefly speaking, when you have no mana to cast, it's taken from your health.</p>
<p class="measure-wide"><em>— Doctor Cat</em></p>
</blockquote></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>