<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>    
        <title>Vlad Kostyanetsky</title>
        <description>Hello! My name is Vlad, I'm business app developer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://kostyanetsky.me</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 12:43:48 +0700</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <title>About PDF</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/pdf</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-pdf</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 12:43:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I get a complaint: a client can’t log into our customer portal. I check the database — the account is fine. So what’s the problem? I check the login and see a strange sight:</p>
<p><img alt="PDF" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/pdf/pdf.png"/></p>
<p>Above is what the user entered, and below is what’s in the database. My first thought: how on earth did a document end up in the string? :D</p>
<p>I’ll skip the further investigation. The key here is asking the right questions (otherwise, both Google and AI will be thinking about the popular file format, not the symbol). So, PDF in the context of Unicode means Pop Directional Formatting! It’s a symbol that controls text direction; it’s needed, for example, to properly render Arabic (which can contain both left-to-right and right-to-left text). The user obviously enters the login in RTL mode (or copies it from somewhere), and the portal does not understand this nuance.</p>
<p>In short, a piece of cake. However, I’d like to point out that the PDF file format existed long before the PDF symbol. I get that these are different technical fields, and the developers probably didn’t see the overlapping terminology as a significant issue. But deep down, I’m sure someone was smirking, anticipating today’s confusion.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Rapture</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/rapture</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-rapture</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 13:27:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I remember how amazed I was when I worked with window functions in PostgreSQL for the first time. You can adjust the calculation window for each row individually! And even segment it in advance. And all this is done natively, within a regular query, no extra add-ons needed. The standard aggregation with grouping and subqueries that I was used to in 1C suddenly turned into a pumpkin, just like Cinderella's carriage at midnight.</p>
<p>Recently, I’ve been learning Blender, and I suddenly felt the same excitement for the same reason. The fact that you can freely move objects around the 3D Viewport with the Move command was clear from the start, fine. However, when it hit me that each object is a set of polygons, and that each polygon can also be moved freely, leading to a natural reshaping of the object's geometry — that’s when it really got me.</p>
<p>Technology is amazing. Learning is awesome. Moments like these make me want to keep doing it over and over again :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Nowhere To Run</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/nowhere-to-run</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-nowhere-to-run</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 13:17:05 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Yesterday, I decided to take a break from work and go for a good run. I headed to the local park and did a few laps. Sitting there catching my breath, I grabbed my phone to switch the track, and there it was — a congratulations from my fitness tracker.</p>
<p><img alt="Oh hi" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/nowhere-to-run/hi.jpg"/></p>
<p>So much for taking a break. The platform is watching you, %username%!</p>
<p>P.S. But hey, now I’ve got a custom badge with the platform's logo. Gotta wear it with pride!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>System Analysis</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/system-analysis-course</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-system-analysis-course</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 14:58:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Amidst all these pet projects and the August whirlwind, I forgot to mention that I completed a <a href="https://tough-dev.school/system-analysis" target="_blank">course</a> on system analysis, which I recently <a href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/ibrahim" target="_blank">wrote about</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="Certificate" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/system-analysis-course/certificate.png"/></p>
<p>The course was structured so that throughout the sessions, we worked on the same system, identifying problems and gradually solving them. Before the first lesson, we were asked to design the initial version of the system so that we could compare it with the final version at the end of the course and assess our progress. Well, I’m happy with the comparison — I mean, it’s really hard to look at that first version without laughing (or crying) :)</p>
<p>There wasn’t much time for reflection during the course, so I plan to continue working on the materials and turning the lessons into personal notes. It’s not that simple, given that our company deals heavily with solutions based on 1C:Enterprise, and much of my work involves various integrations of 1C instances with solutions outside the 1C stack.</p>
<p>However, 1C instances can be considered as monoliths with a specific set of characteristics (depending on the tasks being solved within them), and in most other respects, communication with them doesn’t differ much from traditional solutions: the same events (like RabbitMQ), the same incoming/outgoing HTTP calls, the same instability metric, and so on.</p>
<p>At this point, I’m definitely adopting (or have already adopted):</p>
<ol>
<li>Breaking down the technical specifications into numbered items (US-XXX) and storing them in one place with tags like "updated at," "canceled at," etc. This format seems quite effective.</li>
<li>Maintaining an ADR (Architecture Decision Record). I’ve already implemented this, actually. However, it’s a bit concerning that some items occasionally get stored there that aren’t strictly architectural (e.g., logging principles for certain sections). Still, such things seem crucial for decision-making.</li>
<li>Event Storming as a way to visualize business processes. I can’t say it’s a huge improvement over the patchwork we used before, but the result looks nice, and having a standard is better than having none.</li>
<li>Application service diagrams with stickers indicating each service's characteristics. This is quite functional when you need to look at the project from a high level, and it’s not as dry as endless tables. That way, if the bus factor kicks in, the next person is more likely to notice these details.</li>
<li>I want to work on BPMN and Activity Diagrams. I like the format, but so far, my attempts haven’t been satisfactory. I’ll keep trying.</li>
<li>The concept of separating functionality to reduce dependencies unexpectedly resonated with me. It used to seem simpler to combine similar functionalities to reduce code volume, but now it seems this approach increases complexity and internal cohesion, potentially causing more harm than good.</li>
</ol>
<p>Overall, I’m very satisfied with the course. It seems like the best investment of effort over the past year. If you’re thinking of taking it but are unsure — go for it :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>My First Approach to Gen Models</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/first-pancake</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-first-pancake</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 14:07:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I needed to quickly generate some images for a pet project. I grabbed the first tool at hand — <a href="https://huggingface.co/hakurei/waifu-diffusion" target="_blank">WaifuDiffusion</a> (a clone of <a href="https://huggingface.co/stabilityai/stable-diffusion-3-medium" target="_blank">StableDiffusion</a>, but trained specifically on anime and manga).</p>
<p>Prompt: </p>
<blockquote>
<p>A dimly lit, empty classroom with faintly visible music notes on the chalkboard. A young woman with long blue hair and blue eyes, is standing behind the teacher's desk, packing her things into a small handbag. She looks tired and worried.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Result:</p>
<p><img alt="Young woman" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/first-pancake/young-woman.jpg"/></p>
<p>It seems like a great opportunity to talk about how far neural networks have come! The model instantly got the idea and decided to introduce into the scene... Hmm... A wise bearded man? Or perhaps it was suggesting that I should learn to appreciate unexpected surprises more?</p>
<p>I think WaifuDiffusion just wanted to brighten my mood. They say laughter extends life. In any case, I consider the first generation a success! But it definitely needs some calibration :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Day Switcher for Obsidian</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/obsidian-day-switcher</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-obsidian-day-switcher</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2024 15:11:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>When you're actively working in daily notes in Obsidian, you often want to quickly peek into the note from yesterday or, conversely, for tomorrow. For example, when sorting today's tasks and wanting to postpone some of them for tomorrow.</p>
<p>I'm too lazy to type the exact date every time, so I wrote a <a href="https://gist.github.com/vkostyanetsky/6c70f00b817157f9b6e62ee89bade853" target="_blank">script</a> for this. It takes the note's date from its title (expects it to be in <abbr title="2024-08-17, for example.">ISO 8601</abbr> format) and generates a tooltip with links to yesterday's and tomorrow's notes. The day of the week is displayed in the header for additional convenience:</p>
<p><img alt="Example" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/obsidian-day-switcher/callout.jpg"/></p>
<p>The script is written for the <a href="https://github.com/blacksmithgu/obsidian-dataview" target="_blank">Dataview</a> plugin since I'm already using it for other tasks. In general, it can easily be adapted for <a href="https://github.com/SilentVoid13/Templater" target="_blank">Templater</a>, <a href="https://github.com/saml-dev/obsidian-custom-js" target="_blank">CustomJS</a>, or even turned into a standalone plugin (again, I'm too lazy to bother with that).</p>
<p>If you plan to use it:</p>
<ol>
<li>In the noteLink() function, specify the path to your daily notes folder (currently, the path contains a 'Days' folder for example; I mean the path is indicated in the Daily notes/Template file location setting);</li>
<li>Include the script in your daily note template (Daily notes/Template file location setting).</li>
</ol></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Clementine Will Remember That</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/clementine</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-clementine</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 23:09:32 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>When ChatGPT remembers a detail from a conversation for the future, it displays a "Memory updated" badge above its response. Like, got it:</p>
<p><img alt="Memory updated" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/clementine/memory-updated.jpg"/></p>
<p>Every time I see it, it makes me smile because it instantly reminds me of <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/207610/The_Walking_Dead/" target="_blank">The Walking Dead</a> and the meme “Clementine will remember that”. In that game, the characters surrounding the protagonist would remember his decisions, and it would influence their behavior. This included Clementine — a girl the main character saved at the beginning of the game.</p>
<p><img alt="Clementine will remember that" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/clementine/remember.jpeg"/></p>
<p>In the game, this mechanic was honestly implemented in a rather mediocre way, but when it comes to ChatGPT — it works. The attention to detail is so strong that sometimes I have to remind myself that I’m talking to a language model, not an extraordinarily attentive and very knowledgeable person.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Make Window a Door</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/make-my-window-a-door</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-make-my-window-a-door</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 19:26:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I was listening to <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/33MnSYLvtOrbj5zwfioEiH?si=19fec91123394826" target="_blank">Be Somebody</a> by Thousand Foot Krutch yesterday and suddenly caught the phrase “you made my window a door”. I used to think that this idiom is rather funny: like, damn, the idea to replace a window with a door somehow sounds unsafe. You can fall from the tenth floor, you know?</p>
<p>At the same time, the song is wonderful and not about that at all! I got curious and started digging around to find out what meaning native speakers put into it.</p>
<p>It turned out that it is actually about two different positions: a passive observer and an active participant. That is, if there is a window in front of you, you only look through it at something or someone. But you can open the door and finally do something. Hence, “when I could only see the floor you made my window a door” means something like “when my hands dropped, you helped me up”.</p>
<p>By the way, there is another similar idiom — “to be a better window than a door”. The abstraction here is the same: if a person is like a window, and not a door — they hardly ever let people close to them, making passive observers even out of people very close to them.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Yaga</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/yaga</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-yaga</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 01:21:21 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I accidentally remembered that six months ago, one of my colleagues threw a link to <a href="https://yaga.rt.ru" target="_blank">Yaga</a> into the work chat. It is a future (I guess) competitor of JIRA in Russia. Judging by the URL, the guys from Rostelecom are developing it. Here my curiosity was awakened — how is it there, did it take off?</p>
<p>Alas, but looks like nope. At least, the landing page has the “leave a request and wait for a response beep” vibe. Only a simplified version is available for smaller teams that I can't touch as well: being not in Russia and clicking on the “Start using” button leads me to a ban. Welp, next time, maybe.</p>
<p>The naming is clickbait, of course. But I’m not sure if it’s really a good choice. For example, “1C” may provoke forced jokes (One s! Odin's ass! Haha), but if you google this, you are more likely to find information about the platform or at least the vendor. Not a bunch of articles, fan fiction, fan art, or video games, as in the case of Yaga.</p>
<p>Moreover, some wrong associations come to mind. What does Baba Yaga reminds you of? A hut on chicken legs? It looks like an initially <a href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/evolution" target="_blank">poorly designed</a> application that was somehow remade right on production. A mortar? A crutch? Damn, if you look at it from the point of view of programmers — these are not red flags, but real scarlet banners fluttering in the wind :)</p>
<p>One more thing: I'm probably spoiled, but when I hear the word “Yaga”, the first thing that pops into my head is not a powerful witch from Slavic folklore, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaguar_(drink)" target="_blank">disgusting booze</a> from the 2000s.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Now Baba with Yaga are no longer redneck, but a patriotic programmer!</p>
<p>― colleague</p>
</blockquote></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Ibrahim</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/ibrahim</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-ibrahim</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 20:29:24 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Recently, I took a <a href="https://tough-dev.school/system-analysis" target="_blank">system analysis course</a>, which was taught by the guys from the “School of Strong Programmers”. I have two goals:</p>
<ol>
<li>First, I need to calibrate. I handle a dozen tech stacks that have different tool sets and concepts of beauty. This, of course, is a great development, but it distorts the perspective: I am drawn to solve the next problem, starting with minor technical things, simply because I am good at it. Meanwhile, if you look at the problem a little from above, think about it, and draw some diagrams, you will get a better or at least more meaningful solution. So I want to convince myself to do this more often.</li>
<li>Secondly, I need to learn how to write clear documentation for developers. In practice, I rarely get around to it, and when I do, I don’t have time to keep it up-to-date. In short, time is short, and I would at least like to do the paperwork somehow so that the reader grasps the idea more quickly.</li>
</ol>
<p>The course itself is made in the shape of iterations: every week you are told about the same project that the main character of the story, Ibrahim, is trying to design (that’s him on the landing page in the link above). Every week, there are more and more problems with this project, and the solutions that dude comes up with become more and more intricate.</p>
<p>In addition, students are regularly assigned homework for another project with similar issues. It needs to be analyzed and designed again and again, taking into account the new knowledge and limitations gained over the past week.</p>
<p>So far, it's going great. The main concern is a lack of time. I read relatively slowly and try to take notes on the most captivating or simply difficult passages. Meanwhile, there is a lot of material in the course, and all of it is interesting, even if you count only the main part of the content.</p>
<p>In addition, if you go to the additional links, you can even take away the saints. It takes six months, no less. I tried to read them at least diagonally, but it turned out to be a damn bad idea. I ended up seeing the main character of the course in a street advertisement :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>