<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>    
        <title>Vlad Kostyanetsky</title>
        <description>Hello! My name is Vlad, I'm business app developer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://kostyanetsky.me</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 21:25:48 +0700</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <title>Diablo</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/diablo</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-diablo</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 21:25:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kVd6qeWoAxg" width="560"></iframe>
<p>The nice episode of the “We Are Doomed” IT podcast about developer burnout. No insights, but you can hear something useful for yourself. I liked the analogy with video games, somewhere close to the middle:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There was such a game — Diablo. RPG, all sorts of spells, you know. A character has mana and health, and when you have no mana to cast… Ha, I sound like a nerd! Well, nevermind. Briefly speaking, when you have no mana to cast, it's taken from your health.</p>
<p><em>— Doctor Cat</em></p>
</blockquote></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Beware the Daughter of the Sea</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/jaina</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-jaina</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2018 16:19:10 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Natalia O'Shea has sung a Jaina's song in a Russian version of a trailer for a future update of World of Warcraft. As for me, she's extraordinary good in it — I mean, she knows how to make a proper mood and season a speech with steel.</p>
<iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5j-S448XC8k" width="560"></iframe>
<p>By the way, speaking about her and “Melnitsa” as a whole thing — all of their most powerful songs are about something particular. We were at a concert dedicated to the “Luciferase” release and it's hard to compare, seriously. Perhaps, I didn't know something essential to understanding a context, but sometimes it was even barely possible to figure out a story which I was hearing.</p>
<p>Just watch a video I posted under. You don't need to know something special about the World of Warcraft universe, do you? For example, I haven't played WoW and not planning to do it, but the end of the song literally creeps me out :-)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Message to User</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/message-to-user</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-message-to-user</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 09:37:18 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>1C:Enterprise has a convenient and accustomed method of showing information for a user — it's a UserMessage object. It outputs messages at the bottom of a form and suddenly it's a potential problem. The thing is, most users don't look at it. It's like: well, I see no critical errors for now so there is nothing to worry about.</p>
<p>Therefore, in case an error happens or you just have an essential message, you should show it through a dialogue window — by the ShowQueryBox() method or a ShowMessageBox() method, for example. Otherwise, a user may not notice a problem and continue to work in spite of some action might not be executed or might be executed in a wrong way. The issue will come out later and you will be rightfully blamed for it.</p>
<p>In addition, using of a UserMessage object should be prohibited in case of small service forms. Yes, in fact, it's hard to overlook a text if a window is small, but that's a different matter: the messages below literally <a href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/message-to-user/en.png" target="_blank">devour</a> form's workspace and it becomes hard to work with.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Do Not Confuse</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/do-not-confuse</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-do-not-confuse</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2022 20:09:31 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><img alt="Code" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/do-not-confuse/do-not-confuse.png"/></p>
<p>If the type of operation is the sale of goods or real estate, then open the common form AdvancesPickFormWithVAT with the parameters defined in the PickParameters structure. The callback is EditPrepaymentOffsetEnd method, defined in the same module; pass it the AdditionalParameters structure. The form needs to be opened so that it locks the whole interface.</p>
<p>However, if the type of operation is a return to the supplier, then open the general form AdvancesPickFormWithVAT with the parameters defined in the PickParameters structure. The callback is the EditPrepaymentOffsetEnd method, defined in the same module; pass it the AdditionalParameters structure. The form needs to be opened so that it locks the whole interface.</p>
<p>I hope you won't confuse.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>A Script to Sync With NAS</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/rclone-abuser</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-rclone-abuser</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 19:04:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I posted on GitHub a Python <a href="https://github.com/vkostyanetsky/RCloneAbuser" target="_blank">script</a> which I use to sync files between my PC and a NAS. I have a Synology DS220j; a lot of software comes with it, including a backup utility. However, it seems to have been made for show only: the program began to fail even at the setup stage, so I lost confidence in it pretty fast.</p>
<p>I suffered with the problem for some time and eventually returned to the good old <a href="https://rclone.org" target="_blank">rclone</a>, which has only two problems for me. Firstly, I can't normally connect to an SMB share: yes, the login and password can be saved in Windows and rclone will use them, but OS will forget it as soon as possible. I got out of the situation by connecting my NAS as an external drive.</p>
<p>Secondly, I had many files and folders to sync: a directory here, a directory there, a config from there, a profile from here… In order not to produce spaghetti code, I wrote a simple script that takes sources and receivers from a config file, and then executes rclone for each pair.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Top Salaries</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/top-salaries</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-top-salaries</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2021 16:49:35 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><blockquote>
<p>There is a path to a CSV file. You need to open it, read the header (first line), find the Salary column and display the top 10 salaries.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://t.me/nikitonsky_chat/26402" target="_blank">Link</a></em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Threw in my <a href="https://gist.github.com/tonsky/881d5d8c4fbed818fe2905a7591a91e0#file-vkostyanetsky-1c" target="_blank">two cents</a> just to complete the picture. If you forget about stability, readability, and performance — you can cut it in half. Here it was obvious from the very beginning that it would be shorter in bash and clearer in Python, so I just wrote it as I was used to.</p>
<p>What was useful: there are a bunch of examples in other languages ​​in the comments to the post. Frankly speaking, I haven’t come across some of them; it was really curious to look at the syntax and try to understand the way to solve the task.</p>
<p>In general, the whole story reminded Eugene Stepanishev's <a href="https://bolknote.ru/tags/beer99/" target="_blank">hobby</a> — to write the output of the American “beer song” in all languages ​​in a row. By the way, Tonsky's issue looks as fun for me too — too trivial to seriously compare something on its basis.</p>
<p>What was funny: for a couple of <a href="https://t.me/nikitonsky_pub/201?comment=26703" target="_blank">colleagues</a>, the 1C code caused such acute vision problems that they considered it necessary to report it :-) I partly understand the desire to assert itself on the stereotype “1C is bad, mkay?”, but it's the wrong case. The preference in syntax is nothing but a matter of taste, and besides it, the solution in 1C is no different from solutions in any other language without a built-in library for parsing CSV.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>These Nasty Smartphones</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/these-nasty-smartphones</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-these-nasty-smartphones</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><img alt="Society" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/these-nasty-smartphones/drawing.png"/></p>
<p>The artist is <a href="https://www.patreon.com/adamtots" target="_blank">Adam Ellis</a>.</p>
<p>As for me, it's a great illustration for an everlasting moan “why do you always stare at your smartphone blah blah blah”. A reason is quite simple: people have their friends, books, podcasts, games, and YouTube in their smartphones. It's much more fun than a frowning man or a grim women with guru syndrome next to them, for example.</p>
<p>The same is true of children. Social networks are full of arguments about it, but a reason is still the same: if a teenager flips through pictures in his phone in front of you, you bore him and a problem obviously is you.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>HPMoR</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/hpmor</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-hpmor</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 15:32:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Just finished reading “Harry Potter and Methods of Rationality” — the epic fanfic based on the you-know-whose universe. An author is a tough specialist in the field of artificial intelligence and interesting on his own, but his book is what I insistently <a href="http://hpmor.com/" target="_blank">recommend</a> to read.</p>
<p>First of all, it is the magnificent rethinking of the original saga. Many aspects seem not less fascinating, I may say; moreover, the plot itself is certainly excellent — I read two-thirds of the story without switching <a href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/hpmor/gene-wilder-meme.jpg" target="_blank">Gene Wilder</a> off :-) Nevertheless, the author was skillful enough to make all points meet and finish a storyline in such a pretty way that I had almost nothing to complain about.</p>
<p>In any case, this book is a well way to meet with a lot of scientific and just interesting things which were mentioned along the way. The author is smart and his book is a smart one too.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Second Monitor Management via Console</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/2nd-monitor-and-console</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-2nd-monitor-and-console</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 16 Oct 2021 19:55:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I have two monitors. I use the second one during meetings in Zoom or when playing together with friends (in both cases it's convenient to bring the people's cameras there). There are more examples when it's useful, but often the device is simply idle. In order not to be distracted, I decided to turn it off.</p>
<p>What is the ambush here: it is inconvenient to enable or disable the second monitor via OS (a few clicks, and you need to scroll, and all the time you get confused where to go — in “Screen settings” or “Personalization”). I would like one command, and the command on a hotkey. And, ideally, from the script to rule all this.</p>
<p>I did not find the script, but I found a ready-made utility — MultiMonitorTool. It's free. Works under the Windows 10 without problems. The commands below turn on / off the 2nd monitor:</p>
<pre><code>MultiMonitorTool.exe / disable 2
MultiMonitorTool.exe / enable 2
MultiMonitorTool.exe / switch 2
</code></pre>
<p>For some reason, when you turn on a monitor via enable or switch, it's positioned incorrectly sometimes (for example, before it was turned off, it was on the right, and after turning it on, it was on the left). This is fixable. First, let's save the configuration at the moment when both monitors are on:</p>
<pre><code>MultiMonitorTool.exe / SaveConfig Monitors.cfg
</code></pre>
<p>And then, when you need to turn on the monitor, load the saved config:</p>
<pre><code>MultiMonitorTool.exe / LoadConfig Monitors.cfg
</code></pre>
<p>The utility can do a lot more (for example, one of the commands flips application windows between monitors). Follow the link above for the description.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>No More Google Fonts</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/no-more-google-fonts</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-no-more-google-fonts</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 20:25:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><a href="https://twitter.com/PixelAmbacht/status/1494272370076536840" target="_blank"><img alt="Tweet" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/no-more-google-fonts/snap-tweet-PixelAmbacht-1494272370076536840.png"/></a></p>
<p>A year ago, damn it. Okay, hello everyone! Johnny Slowpoke is here! Today we will throw out Google Fonts from my blog. I used to load the main font (PT Sans) from this service, but it makes almost no sense without cross-domain caching. Frankly speaking, the only point to do this further is if a server on which the site is running is slow, so it is faster to load fonts from Google. </p>
<p>I host my blog on GitHub servers and have no complaints about performance. So, I'm self-hosting PT Sans now, and you know what? The difference is dramatic. When updating a page before, there was clearly a noticeable delay between loading the page and loading the font. For now, it is barely recognizable. If you have a blog and want to try to self-host fonts — here is a cool <a href="https://google-webfonts-helper.herokuapp.com/fonts" target="_blank">service</a> that solves the problem in a few clicks.</p>
<p>Don't forget to put a big, nice star on the <a href="https://github.com/majodev/google-webfonts-helper" target="_blank">repository</a>!</p></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>