<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>    
        <title>Vlad Kostyanetsky</title>
        <description>Hello! My name is Vlad, I'm business app developer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://kostyanetsky.me</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 05:21:32 +0700</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Ninth Wave</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/ninth-wave</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-ninth-wave</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 05:21:32 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Yesterday morning, I was buying gifts for my women. While a florist was makings bouquets for me, we had a small talk and I suddenly caught her eye. She was looking at the growing crowd of customers with calmness and a clearly readable shadow of doom. This is probably how sailors looking at a surging wave which is about to bury their boat :-)</p>
<p>People outside the flower industry grin sometimes — they say, eight of March is such a magical holiday for all the florists who make a fortune in ten hours. Well, income is really good these days, but literally anybody who has ever worked in this sphere more often associates the holiday (and a couple of days before it, by the way) with a monstrous strain on health and nerves.</p>
<p>I can say that I got off cheaply: was just deploying and servicing some IT of a local net of flower shops, nothing more (by the way, I want to proudly <a href="http://rosetta.florist/" target="_blank">recommend</a> my former colleagues!). Nonetheless, the smell of flowers caused me Vietnam syndrome for a long time :-)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>New Fastimer</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/fastimer-1-3-1</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-fastimer-1-3-1</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 20:58:32 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Released a new <a href="https://github.com/vkostyanetsky/Fastimer/releases/tag/v1.3.1" target="_blank">version</a> of my console timer for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermittent_fasting" target="_blank">intermittent fasting</a>. I wrote this app about a year ago, when I was once again upset by the <a href="https://www.zerolongevity.com/" target="_blank">Zero</a> application for Android: some very primitive functions (like viewing a specific interval) did not work. Oh my gosh, guys, you had one job!</p>
<p>The main difference between 1.3.1 and 1.2.3 is that the console menu has been cut to hell in favor of the good old arguments and options. The menu concept looks convenient only if an application has few features. However, as soon as you take a step forward, the need to answer a list of questions each time you need something starts to irritate you.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Haul Trucks</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/haul-trucks</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-haul-trucks</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 09:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><img alt="Cars" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/haul-trucks/cars.jpg"/></p>
<p>The colleague grumbled that if you think like that, then the configurator will be Zhiguli, and the EDT will be Kama1 (this is an electric car that has been developed somewhere in the depths of KAMAZ for many years and still can’t gather strength and, finally, show the wonder to the world).</p>
<p>Well, I try to look at things with optimism. I think the platform and its IDE are such haul trucks. No one in their right mind rides them on household chores, but these beasts are irreplaceable on a cut!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Infostart Event 2021</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/infostart-event-2021</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-infostart-event-2021</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 23:40:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Last week I visited Moscow for <a href="https://event.infostart.ru/2021_msk/" target="_blank">Infostart Event 2021</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Listen to numbers of interesting reports — check;</li>
<li>Meet a few cool people in real life — check;</li>
<li>Chat with friends — check!</li>
</ul>
<p>As a result, I suddenly felt rested despite the flights, stress, and fuss. I think it's because I'm working remotely, so it was really cool to look at so many colleagues in real life (not as a stream of electrons, I mean).</p>
<p>In order not to <s>get up</s> to fly twice, I passed the <a href="https://postgrespro.ru/education/exam/DBA1-10" target="_blank">first test</a> for PostgreSQL administration in the PostgresPro office. There are three more tests ahead, and the final one does not exist at all yet — but the walking one will master the road, I guess.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Diablo</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/diablo</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-diablo</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 21:25:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kVd6qeWoAxg" width="560"></iframe>
<p>The nice episode of the “We Are Doomed” IT podcast about developer burnout. No insights, but you can hear something useful for yourself. I liked the analogy with video games, somewhere close to the middle:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There was such a game — Diablo. RPG, all sorts of spells, you know. A character has mana and health, and when you have no mana to cast… Ha, I sound like a nerd! Well, nevermind. Briefly speaking, when you have no mana to cast, it's taken from your health.</p>
<p><em>— Doctor Cat</em></p>
</blockquote></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Wrong Freeway Entrance</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/wrong-freeway-entrance</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-wrong-freeway-entrance</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 09:34:10 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><blockquote>
<p>Have you ever taken the wrong freeway entrance? You need to drive to the next exit to turn around, but you hate every inch of travel because you're going away from your goal.</p>
<p><em>― Andy Weir, "The Martian"</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Programmers have exactly the same emotions when they spend a long time working on something. They suddenly realize that part of it should be designed differently. Moreover, this is exactly what you have to do since it solves several problems at once. This is where technical debt is born. </p>
<p>However, right now you don’t change anything but continue to work with the part of the code that already exists. After all, you are professional, and you have a release date! You have to make it on time and then pay the debt, but you hate every inch of code you write because you're going away from your goal.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Double “i”</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/double-i</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-double-i</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 14:07:40 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I was trying to understand how to transliterate my surname properly yesterday. Ministry of Foreign Affairs says it should be written as “Kostianetskii” in English — with double “i” at the end. It's the quite rare combination: “skiing” is the only frequency word that I'm able to remember.</p>
<p>It caused my curiosity and I googled it. The possible reason I came across is funny: cursive writing! Double “i” looks well only on a computer screen but it suddenly turns into “u” when you try to write it on paper.</p>
<p>More details are <a href="https://spellingisnotcrazy.weebly.com/blog/category/the-letter-i" target="_blank">here</a>.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Matryoshka</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/matryoshka</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-matryoshka</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 17:14:56 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>A few days ago, there was a link to 1Ci certificate in the team chat (a colleague passed their junior <a href="https://academy.1ci.com/courses/1c-junior-developer" target="_blank">course</a>). I go over and see no auth form, no errors — I just get a PDF file. Everything is OK, right? Well, then I open the file:</p>
<p><img alt="Error.pdf" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/matryoshka/not-your-certificate.png"/></p>
<p>Honestly, I am even delighted. We need to implement this UX in our products: you press, for example, the “print” button for a document, and it gives you a PDF! And inside it — a link to another PDF! And inside it — “entity is not filled”, so go fill.</p>
<p>You can sell it as a Russian way of dealing with errors. This is, like, for historical reasons! Blame all the damned matryoshkas, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koschei" target="_blank">Koschei</a> with his needle. It is, as you remember, in the egg, and it is in the duck, which is in the rabbit, tucked into the chest, and further along the chain of nesting.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Romania&#x27;s Feature</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/crossed</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-crossed</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2023 01:02:24 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Making a password recover function via SMS for our customer portal. Got to the Twilio <a href="https://support.twilio.com/hc/en-us/articles/223133767-International-support-for-Alphanumeric-Sender-ID" target="_blank">documentation</a> related to <a href="https://www.twilio.com/docs/glossary/what-alphanumeric-sender-id" target="_blank">alphanumeric sender ID</a> support in different countries; this feature allows you to send messages so that the recipient sees not the sender's number but something meaningful (a company name, for example).</p>
<p>The feature is regulated differently everywhere: in some countries it just works, but in others registration is possible or even required.</p>
<p>Well, let's take a look:</p>
<p><img alt="Screenshot" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/crossed/twilio.png"/></p>
<p>🤔</p>
<ul>
<li>Portugal: yes</li>
<li>Puerto Rico: no</li>
<li>Qatar: yes (with registration)</li>
<li>Reunion: yes</li>
<li>Romania: yes (with registration) (but be afraid of Dracula)</li>
</ul>
<p>I don’t know how else I can explain this cemetery.</p>
<p>UPD: Found the answer. Grave crosses mean you have to pay $700 to register.</p>
<p>To be frank, I like the explanation about Dracula much more.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>A Principle of Non-Judgemental Attitude</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/non-judgmental-attitude</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-non-judgmental-attitude</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Sep 2018 16:36:53 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>There is a good <a href="http://maximilyahov.ru/blog/all/mne-ok/" target="_blank">note</a> from Maxim Ilyahov about a way of analyzing something which doesn't concern you but annoys you anyway. It's reminded me of an American principle of non-judgemental attitude which I read about a couple of years ago. As for me, it uses different words to make the same point.</p>
<p>By the way, this principle presents in Russia too — there is even a famous adage “don't be judgemental so you won't be judged”. What a pity for us that it isn't so widespread yet.</p></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>