<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>    
        <title>Vlad Kostyanetsky</title>
        <description>Hello! My name is Vlad, I'm business app developer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://kostyanetsky.me</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 09:12:34 +0700</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <title>Going Postal</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/going-postal</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-going-postal</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 09:12:34 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Recently, I was working with vocabulary in an attempt to describe my latest adventures to an English-speaking friend and got to know about the colorful idiom “to go postal”. It means something like “go crazy with anger”; appeared somewhere between the 80s and 90s in the USA after a series of rather <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Going_postal" target="_blank">insane incidents</a> in which postal workers went crazy and attacked people around, including colleagues and visitors.</p>
<p>The expression sounds funny at first glance, but the story behind the scenes is painfully gloomy. I think I will continue to use the good old “to go ballistic”. Literally, “get angry that strong so you become a rocket which lost control”. Or, to simplify, “explode with anger”.</p>
<p>By the way, there are similar rocket-like connotations in Russian, but for some reason they are about a more manageable cases. Mostly, they implies something like "the fire in the ass was so damn strong that the poor guy left Earth and successfully landed on Mars". Sounds a bit better than a simple explosion — you didn't completely waste the precious resource, at least :-)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Slow down, I&#x27;m recording</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/outgoing-requests-limiter</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-outgoing-requests-limiter</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 15:54:51 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Usually the idea of developing is simple: the faster it works, the better. For example, the more requests an application manages to execute per unit of time, the faster the task for which these requests are needed will be solved.</p>
<p>However, it also happens the other way around: you need to reduce the number of operations that a program is able to perform. Let's imagine we exchange data with an external service and it bans if we hit it with requests too often. For example: the cloud version of <a href="https://bitrix24.net" target="_blank">Bitrix24</a> requires sending requests to it no more than two per second.</p>
<p>Here is an <a href="https://github.com/vkostyanetsky/OutgoingRequestsLimiter" target="_blank">implementation</a> of such a slowdown, which I wrote last week. There is no queue support; the main solved problem is to execute as many requests as possible without going beyond the limit (taking into account the fact that requests can be made from different sessions).</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>No More Google Fonts</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/no-more-google-fonts</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-no-more-google-fonts</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 20:25:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><a href="https://twitter.com/PixelAmbacht/status/1494272370076536840" target="_blank"><img alt="Tweet" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/no-more-google-fonts/snap-tweet-PixelAmbacht-1494272370076536840.png"/></a></p>
<p>A year ago, damn it. Okay, hello everyone! Johnny Slowpoke is here! Today we will throw out Google Fonts from my blog. I used to load the main font (PT Sans) from this service, but it makes almost no sense without cross-domain caching. Frankly speaking, the only point to do this further is if a server on which the site is running is slow, so it is faster to load fonts from Google. </p>
<p>I host my blog on GitHub servers and have no complaints about performance. So, I'm self-hosting PT Sans now, and you know what? The difference is dramatic. When updating a page before, there was clearly a noticeable delay between loading the page and loading the font. For now, it is barely recognizable. If you have a blog and want to try to self-host fonts — here is a cool <a href="https://google-webfonts-helper.herokuapp.com/fonts" target="_blank">service</a> that solves the problem in a few clicks.</p>
<p>Don't forget to put a big, nice star on the <a href="https://github.com/majodev/google-webfonts-helper" target="_blank">repository</a>!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>These Nasty Smartphones</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/these-nasty-smartphones</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-these-nasty-smartphones</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><img alt="Society" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/these-nasty-smartphones/drawing.png"/></p>
<p>The artist is <a href="https://www.patreon.com/adamtots" target="_blank">Adam Ellis</a>.</p>
<p>As for me, it's a great illustration for an everlasting moan “why do you always stare at your smartphone blah blah blah”. A reason is quite simple: people have their friends, books, podcasts, games, and YouTube in their smartphones. It's much more fun than a frowning man or a grim women with guru syndrome next to them, for example.</p>
<p>The same is true of children. Social networks are full of arguments about it, but a reason is still the same: if a teenager flips through pictures in his phone in front of you, you bore him and a problem obviously is you.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Sebby x Player</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/sebby-x-player</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-sebby-x-player</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I have <a href="https://acomics.ru/~sebby-x-player" target="_blank">translated</a> Stardew Valley fan manga on a wave of enthusiasm at the end of July (SV is an enormously addictive farmer simulator which <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/413150/Stardew_Valley/" target="_blank">went out</a> a couple of years ago).</p>
<p>It was an amusing experience. Firstly, an author of the manga is Chinese and her work was already translated from Chinese to English. I'm not sure what was the bigger problem — cultural differences or language skills, but several frames were a bit difficult to understand what's going on. Secondly, I've figured out that it's a real challenge to pick proper Russian words and not to get something like a quote from an official government's letter in the end.</p>
<p>So, a part of sense had lost during the process, I guess, although I tried to keep everything I could and even had a word with the author in order to solve the most problematic cases. It was quite funny — I don't know Chinese, she doesn't know Russian, so our a bit poor English was the only way to understand each other.</p>
<p>Something could have been translated better, I suppose, and several pictures definitely could have been changed more accurately. But you know what? Hell it out, perfection is a cruel mistress and I like the result yet. Yeah, there is no big deal or something like it — a drawing style is quite common, a plot has no significant differences with the game, but… I don't know. Perhaps, visual novels made a too sentimental son of a bitch out of me :-)</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://vk.com/id54890849" target="_blank">Alice</a> for helping me with image processing, <a href="https://twitter.com/amish77kin" target="_blank">Lem</a> for helping me with the translation and <a href="https://vk.com/mahrunteka" target="_blank">Marika</a> for the inspiration. And, sure, thanks to <a href="https://curayukie.deviantart.com" target="_blank">Quantus</a> for the manga.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Top Salaries</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/top-salaries</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-top-salaries</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2021 16:49:35 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><blockquote>
<p>There is a path to a CSV file. You need to open it, read the header (first line), find the Salary column and display the top 10 salaries.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://t.me/nikitonsky_chat/26402" target="_blank">Link</a></em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Threw in my <a href="https://gist.github.com/tonsky/881d5d8c4fbed818fe2905a7591a91e0#file-vkostyanetsky-1c" target="_blank">two cents</a> just to complete the picture. If you forget about stability, readability, and performance — you can cut it in half. Here it was obvious from the very beginning that it would be shorter in bash and clearer in Python, so I just wrote it as I was used to.</p>
<p>What was useful: there are a bunch of examples in other languages ​​in the comments to the post. Frankly speaking, I haven’t come across some of them; it was really curious to look at the syntax and try to understand the way to solve the task.</p>
<p>In general, the whole story reminded Eugene Stepanishev's <a href="https://bolknote.ru/tags/beer99/" target="_blank">hobby</a> — to write the output of the American “beer song” in all languages ​​in a row. By the way, Tonsky's issue looks as fun for me too — too trivial to seriously compare something on its basis.</p>
<p>What was funny: for a couple of <a href="https://t.me/nikitonsky_pub/201?comment=26703" target="_blank">colleagues</a>, the 1C code caused such acute vision problems that they considered it necessary to report it :-) I partly understand the desire to assert itself on the stereotype “1C is bad, mkay?”, but it's the wrong case. The preference in syntax is nothing but a matter of taste, and besides it, the solution in 1C is no different from solutions in any other language without a built-in library for parsing CSV.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Cookie Jar</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/cookie-jar</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-cookie-jar</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 21:34:38 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>The other day, I was working with cookies in one of my scripts. While searching for the optimal solution, I came across an absolutely charming (100% working, by the way) <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/13030095/how-to-save-requests-python-cookies-to-a-file" target="_blank">tip</a> from StackOverflow:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You can get a CookieJar object from the session with session.cookies, and use pickle to store it to a file.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So, literally: keep your cookies in a jar, and to store them, pickle them. The jar with pickled cookies, by the way, can be put on the shelf later.</p>
<p>How can you not love python after that, huh?</p>
<p>P.S. While writing this post, I got curious – why pickle and not serialization? So, briefly: <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/27324986/pickles-why-are-they-called-that/27325007#27325007" target="_blank">this is the way</a>.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>In a Pedantic Way</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/in-a-pedantic-way</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-in-a-pedantic-way</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 20:26:43 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>The daily award for the most philosophical code goes to the author of this elegant way to check that two boolean variables are not equal to each other:</p>
<pre><code>If DataStructure.Property("AmountVATIn")
    And ((DataStructure.AmountVATIn And NOT SearchPriceIncludesVAT)
    OR (NOT DataStructure.AmountVATIn And SearchPriceIncludesVAT)) Then    
    Price = RecalculateAmountOnVATFlagsChange(Price, DataStructure.AmountVATIn, TabSectionLine.VATRate);
EndIf;
</code></pre>
<p>I'm thinking of adding something like “And Not (DataStructure.AmountVATIn = SearchPriceIncludesVAT)” here to spice it up with a subtle note of insanity.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>HPMoR Printing</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/hpmor-printing</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-hpmor-printing</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 19:00:55 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Perhaps you already know that Eliezer Yudkowsky's “Methods of Rationality” in Russian is going to be published as a standard book (thanks to “Evolution” and other information partners), but I still want to remind again.</p>
<p>The book is really good, I had <a href="https://kostyanetsky.me//notes/hpmor" target="_blank">written</a> about it a couple of years ago. It teaches useful things in such an attractive way that it's really hard to stop reading. The whole text is in public access, but if you want a hard copy — you can <a href="https://planeta.ru/campaigns/hpmor" target="_blank">make a request</a> now.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Why So Serious?</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/why-so-serious</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-why-so-serious</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Sometimes when you developing some complex mechanic you don't have enough time time for the adequate naming of variables. As a result, there is a lot of mysterious WhatTheHeck, ApplyMagic and bunch of other LivingFailures.</p>
<p>It's what you should avoid despite it looks funny. You'll rewrite code you've written month or two later and it will be hard to shame its author because it is you.</p></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>