<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>    
        <title>Vlad Kostyanetsky</title>
        <description>Hello! My name is Vlad, I'm business app developer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://kostyanetsky.me</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 22:40:24 +0700</lastBuildDate>
        
        <item>
            <title>A Little Bit Of Surgery</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/bit-of-surgery</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-bit-of-surgery</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 22:40:24 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>A few years ago, I stumbled upon a story about a programmer who had to debug software controlling a surgical robot — right in the middle of an operation. That blew my mind.</p>
<p>Today, my colleague and I were fixing a 1C cluster with databases running on 1cFresh. After migrating it to a neighboring server, the thing suddenly started acting up. Long story short: trying to print a document would send the client app into its death throes.  </p>
<p>While we were knee-deep in troubleshooting, I had this thought: sure, it doesn’t <strong>look</strong> as terrifying as debugging software that someone’s life literally depends on. But if you think about all the clients sitting on edge because their business is grinding to a halt... Well, who knows where the stress levels are higher?  </p>
<p><strong>P.S. Nerdy details for the curious.</strong> During the migration, the permissions for the server cache folder didn’t transfer properly. This led to a funny (well, not so funny) effect: the logs would happily land there, but session data wouldn’t.  </p>
<p>So, when someone opened a print form, the configuration tried saving it to the storage, and rphost, in turn, attempted to shove it into the session cache. Here’s where things went sideways: the worker' process (probably) got slapped on the wrist by the OS. Due to (apparently) some funky file system event handling in the platform, the exception wasn’t caught, so the poor thing had no better idea than to kill the session on the server. Naturally, this caused the client process to crash.  </p>
<p>We fixed the permissions, rebooted the cluster, and voilà! The problem was gone.  </p>
<p><img alt="End of Report" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/bit-of-surgery/report.jpeg"/></p>
<p>All other hypotheses — cluster manager acting up, lack of hardware resources, configuration bugs, client-side issues, broken security profiles, network problems between the client and server — got tossed out during the diagnostics process.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Vaguely Familiar Logo</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/vaporia</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-vaporia</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 17:37:06 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p><del>Meanwhile, OpenAI opened a branch in Tbilisi</del> Actually, they just sell vapes here, and the logo designer was probably inspired by clouds of smoke. But every time I walk by, it still catches my eye :)</p>
<p><img alt="Vaporia" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/vaporia/vaporia.jpg"/></p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Creepy Graveyard</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/creepy-graveyard</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-creepy-graveyard</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 23:23:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Still learning 3D in my free time. Here's my first somewhat independent project after finishing a <a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/blender-environments-megacourse-create-3d-environments/" target="_blank">course</a> recently.</p>
<p><a href="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/creepy-graveyard/creepy-graveyard.png" target="_blank"><img alt="Creepy Graveyard" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/creepy-graveyard/creepy-graveyard.png"/></a></p>
<iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mraGFR_Tr5k" width="560"></iframe>
<p>Of course, there are plenty of issues: the models, the colors, the composition... Honestly, pretty much everything. Good thing the scene is set at night with fog, so it's easy to hide the worst spots. I wouldn't be surprised if the course creators picked this setting on purpose to keep beginners from getting too discouraged :)</p>
<p>That said, I'm happy with the result. At this stage, perfectionism feels more like an enemy than a friend. And hey, it’s definitely better than my last attempt! Back then, I was totally green in Blender and scared to deviate even slightly from the instructor: ten minutes of watching, ten minutes of copying.</p>
<p>That approach works at the very beginning, but it doesn't help you learn how to solve problems. This time, I watched a few lessons back-to-back for about an hour or two, then tried to figure things out on my own. I only went back to the videos when I was completely stuck. Feels like I’m actually retaining a lot more this way.</p>
<p>Long story short, the thing is done. On to the next one!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Summary to Slack</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/slack-summary</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-slack-summary</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 13:22:54 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I found a <a href="https://gist.github.com/vkostyanetsky/b0807f2df2501bbeeb97c95a977f3e23" target="_blank">script</a> that I wrote a couple of years ago for our work GitLab. In short, we run our development repository through a barrage of tests on Vanessa daily, resulting in a nice report showing how many tests passed, which ones failed, the reasons for failures, and so on.</p>
<p>The report needs to be analyzed regularly, at least at a glance. Of course, we haven’t seen fully "green" tests in a long time, and that’s expected: for example, in the case of interdependent development, commits can break the checked functionality, and the tests still need adjustments. However, keeping a pulse on it is still essential.</p>
<p>To simplify this routine, I expanded the pipeline code a bit: after generating the report, GitLab first creates a brief summary (client type, database type, test statistics) and sends it to Slack.</p>
<p><img alt="Report" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/slack-summary/report.jpg"/></p>
<p>As a bonus, it’s now easier to answer the philosophical question, "who broke everything". Most often, it’s the author of the first commit on which the Scenarios Failed metric in the screenshot above hit the ceiling :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Log &amp; Bug</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/butterfly</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-butterfly</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 20:45:16 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I love digging into the origins of words from time to time. For example, "log" comes from maritime terminology and literally means a log: a wooden float attached to a rope, which was thrown overboard from a ship. The rope had knots tied at regular intervals, and by counting how many knots unwound in a certain amount of time, sailors could determine the speed of the ship.</p>
<p>These measurements were recorded in the ship's journal, which was also called a log. Over time, the term started being used for any kind of record or journal of events, and in IT, the word got a second life :)</p>
<p>Or take "bug" — well, you’ve probably heard about this one. A moth, which messed with a computer’s operation over seventy years ago, was documented in the log as "the first actual case of a bug being found". The insect gained a kind of digital immortality: now any mistake, especially in a program, is called a bug.</p>
<p>(It’s just a pity that it wasn’t a prettier insect — like a butterfly, for instance? That would’ve added a touch of romance to our work)</p>
<p>(Though, if you think about it... maybe "bug" isn’t such a bad option after all. "Butterfly" is a bit too long. Besides, someone would’ve shortened it to "butt," and right now, we’d be fixing butts instead of bugs)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>ChatGPT Mimicry</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-love</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 14:57:41 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Colleagues are actively <a href="https://t.me/denissexy/8767" target="_blank">experimenting</a> with o1-preview from OpenAI: the model turned out to be genuinely interesting. Unfortunately, tasks for it don’t come up too often — regular 4o handles most day-to-day stuff just fine. Bug-finding in code, analyzing medical tests in an unfamiliar language, or trying to recall the name of a childhood book with only a vague recollection of the plot — I can’t easily think of anything it wouldn’t handle.</p>
<p>It’s always fascinating to see how the AI reasons, jokes, and generally tries to act human. I’d say it won’t pass the Turing test just yet, but every now and then, it comes eerily close.</p>
<p><img alt="Carrot" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love/carrot.jpg"/> <img alt="Fists" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love/fists.jpg"/> <img alt="Jokes" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love/joke.jpg"/></p>
<p>The answer below made me smile. Even leaving philosophy aside — looks like Skynet is off the table! :) Though, I’m afraid the future from the <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/282140/SOMA/" target="_blank">SOMA</a> ending is still possible.</p>
<p><img alt="Love" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/love/love.jpg"/></p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Cool Stuff!</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/thumbs-up</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-thumbs-up</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 11:59:34 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>A knock at the door. I open it, and there are two bright, twenty-something girls standing there. Flashing huge smiles at me, they start talking a mile a minute.</p>
<p>The Georgian language is beautiful, but I haven’t gotten around to learning it yet. I sigh and suggest we switch to English or Russian.</p>
<p>The girls frown a little. Then one of them digs into her bag, pulls out a flyer, points to it, gives me a thumbs up like, “cool stuff!” — and hands it to me. </p>
<p>Then they laugh and run off.</p>
<p>Take that, language barrier!</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>About PDF</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/pdf</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-pdf</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 12:43:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I get a complaint: a client can’t log into our customer portal. I check the database — the account is fine. So what’s the problem? I check the login and see a strange sight:</p>
<p><img alt="PDF" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/pdf/pdf.png"/></p>
<p>Above is what the user entered, and below is what’s in the database. My first thought: how on earth did a document end up in the string? :D</p>
<p>I’ll skip the further investigation. The key here is asking the right questions (otherwise, both Google and AI will be thinking about the popular file format, not the symbol). So, PDF in the context of Unicode means Pop Directional Formatting! It’s a symbol that controls text direction; it’s needed, for example, to properly render Arabic (which can contain both left-to-right and right-to-left text). The user obviously enters the login in RTL mode (or copies it from somewhere), and the portal does not understand this nuance.</p>
<p>In short, a piece of cake. However, I’d like to point out that the PDF file format existed long before the PDF symbol. I get that these are different technical fields, and the developers probably didn’t see the overlapping terminology as a significant issue. But deep down, I’m sure someone was smirking, anticipating today’s confusion.</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Rapture</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/rapture</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-rapture</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 13:27:48 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>I remember how amazed I was when I worked with window functions in PostgreSQL for the first time. You can adjust the calculation window for each row individually! And even segment it in advance. And all this is done natively, within a regular query, no extra add-ons needed. The standard aggregation with grouping and subqueries that I was used to in 1C suddenly turned into a pumpkin, just like Cinderella's carriage at midnight.</p>
<p>Recently, I’ve been learning Blender, and I suddenly felt the same excitement for the same reason. The fact that you can freely move objects around the 3D Viewport with the Move command was clear from the start, fine. However, when it hit me that each object is a set of polygons, and that each polygon can also be moved freely, leading to a natural reshaping of the object's geometry — that’s when it really got me.</p>
<p>Technology is amazing. Learning is awesome. Moments like these make me want to keep doing it over and over again :)</p></description>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Nowhere To Run</title>
            <link>https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/nowhere-to-run</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">note-nowhere-to-run</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 13:17:05 +0700</pubDate>
            <description><p>Yesterday, I decided to take a break from work and go for a good run. I headed to the local park and did a few laps. Sitting there catching my breath, I grabbed my phone to switch the track, and there it was — a congratulations from my fitness tracker.</p>
<p><img alt="Oh hi" src="https://kostyanetsky.me/notes/nowhere-to-run/hi.jpg"/></p>
<p>So much for taking a break. The platform is watching you, %username%!</p>
<p>P.S. But hey, now I’ve got a custom badge with the platform's logo. Gotta wear it with pride!</p></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>